now it often happens that when doing
something like an examine tomasulo's
algorithm we just care for example like
in what cycle something issues on in
what cycles something finishes and so on
or how many cycles it took overall so
let's go to an example that is just
trying to track the timing and not
trying to keep track of everything in
every structure and so on just to kind
of show you how to do these on exams so
we will have the same processor the same
instructions the same issue executes
right but we're going to try to do that
without having all of those tables in so
let's try to go to this example what's
going to happen is we kind of need to
know how many reservation stations we
have for each type of instructions and
that's the only thing that we're kind of
gonna be missing a little bit so
basically in the first cycle we know we
can issue this and nothing else will
happen in the next cycle we know we can
execute this and then because it takes
three cycles we know that we're gonna
try to write it in cycle four so kind of
marked is tentatively now for cycle four
in the next cycle we will be issuing
this load here if we consider the same
condition that the load cannot overlap
with another load and we know that in
two and three this is going to execute
so that this can begin execution in four
and then executed five and try to
broadcast in six in cycle three we're
gonna be issuing this it uses a
different unit so again you have to
check basically in cycle three is there
an available multiply unit but kind of
looking at what's currently using the
reservation stations and then you have
to check for dependencies so for example
this is waiting for F 2 and F 4 F 2 is
produced by the second load so actually
this will not be able to execute until
cycle 7 6 here means that basically we
will have 7 and we can kind of mark here
that our F 2 comes from instruction 2
which is why we had to execute only in
the cycle that follows it's right
because this is a multiplication add 10
cycles to that we're gonna try to write
the result in cycle 17 the subtract is
gonna issue in the very next cycle if
there are available reservation stations
because so far we have used no add
reservation stations that's going to be
able to issue the subtract is going to
wait for 2 & 6 so
the later of the two loads is really
when we can start so we can start in
cycle seven and we will mark here again
that you know we are waiting kind of
just give an indication what was the
delay somewhere and then it's a subtract
so it's gonna finish in cycle a seven
eight
so it's gonna try to write the result in
nine next we're gonna consider this
divide can it issue in cycle five well
yes it can because so far only one unit
is used and we have two such only one
reservation station is used and we have
two of them so the question is when can
it execute well look for F 0 and F 6 F 0
comes from the multiply at 17 F 6 comes
at 4 so we will be able to execute in
cycle 18 here because we were waiting
for F 0 like this and it's a divide so
it's gonna try to broadcast at cycle 58
next we're going to consider what's the
next issue cycle well 6 this ad is gonna
issue in 6 because again we have units I
just wanna look for f8 and f2 whichever
is the latest to is at 6 F 8 is 8 9 so
it's gonna start executing in cycle 10
executing cycle 11 try to broadcast in
cycle 12 and we're going to mark that F
8 comes from instruction 4 and now
because we've been kind of doing this
out of order we have to check just are
there any two instructions that are
actually writing in the same cycle if
yes then we'll have to redo this
basically we have to postpone some of
the writes in order for that to happen
but because these are all different
cycles everything is fine and this
concludes our timing examples so
basically now we know in which cycle
each instruction executes issues and
writes and when does this all end
without really having to go through all
of those things so if we are only
worried about timing then we can do
something like this